<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>Box Backup Build and Installation Guide</title>

  <preface>
    <title>License</title>

    <para>Copyright &copy; 2003 - 2007, Ben Summers and contributors.
    All rights reserved.</para>

    <para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
    modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
    met:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
        notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above
        copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer
        in the documentation and/or other materials provided with the
        distribution.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All use of this software and associated advertising materials
        must display the following acknowledgement: This product includes
        software developed by Ben Summers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The names of the Authors may not be used to endorse or promote
        products derived from this software without specific prior written
        permission.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <para>[Where legally impermissible the Authors do not disclaim liability
    for direct physical injury or death caused solely by defects in the
    software unless it is modified by a third party.]</para>

    <para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS
    OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED
    WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
    PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS BE LIABLE FOR
    ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
    DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS
    OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
    HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT,
    STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING
    IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE
    POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
  </preface>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The backup daemon, bbackupd, runs on all machines to be backed up.
    The store server daemon, bbstored runs on a central server. Data is sent
    to the store server, which stores all data on local filesystems, that is,
    only on local hard drives. Tape or other archive media is not used.</para>

    <para>The system is designed to be easy to set up and run, and cheap to
    use. Once set up, there should be no need for user or administrative
    intervention, apart from usual system maintenance.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Client daemon</title>

      <para>bbackupd is configured with a list of directories to back up. It
      has a lazy approach to backing up data. Every so often, the directories
      are scanned, and new data is uploaded to the server. This new data must
      be over a set age before it is uploaded. This prevents rapid revisions
      of a file resulting in many uploads of the same file in a short period
      of time.</para>

      <para>It can also operate in a snapshot mode, which behaves like
      traditional backup software. When instructed by an external bbackupctl
      program, it will upload all changed files to the server.</para>

      <para>The daemon is always running, although sleeping most of the time.
      In lazy mode, it is completely self contained -- scripts running under
      cron jobs are not used. The objective is to keep files backed up, not to
      make snapshots of the filesystem at particular points in time
      available.</para>

      <para>If an old version of the file is present on the server, a modified
      version of the rsync algorithm is used to upload only the changed
      portions of the file.</para>

      <para>After a new version is uploaded, the old version is still
      available (subject to disc space on the server). Similarly, a deleted
      file is still available. The only limit to their availability is space
      allocated to this account on the server</para>

      <para>Future versions will add the ability to mark the current state of
      files on the server, and restore from this mark. This will emulate the
      changing of tapes in a tape backup system.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Restoration</title>

        <para>Restoring files is performed using a query tool, bbackupquery.
        This can be used to restore entire directories, or as an 'FTP-like'
        tool to list and retrieve individual files. Old versions and deleted
        files can be retrieved using this tool for as long as they are kept on
        the server.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Client Resource Usage</title>

        <para>bbackupd uses only a minimal amount of disc space to store
        records on uploaded files -- less than 32 bytes per directory and file
        over a set size threshold. However, it minimises the amount of queries
        it must make to the server by storing, in memory, a data structure
        which allows it to determine what data is new. It does not need to
        store a record of all files, essentially just the directory names and
        last modification times. This is not a huge amount of memory.</para>

        <para>If there are no changes to the directories, then the client will
        not even connect to the server.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Security</title>

      <para>Box Backup is designed to be secure in several ways. The data
      stored on the backup store server is encrypted using secret-key
      cryptography. Additionally, the transport layer is encrypted using TLS,
      to ensure that the communications can't be snooped.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Encryption</title>

        <para>The files, directories, filenames and file attributes are all
        encrypted. By examining the stored files on the server, it is only
        possible to determine the approximate sizes of a files and the tree
        structure of the disc (not names, just number of files and
        subdirectories in a directory). By monitoring the actions performed by
        a client, it is possible to determine the frequency and approximate
        scope of changes to files and directories.</para>

        <para>The connections between the server and client are encrypted
        using TLS (latest version of SSL). Traffic analysis is possible to
        some degree, but limited in usefulness.</para>

        <para>An attacker will not be able to recover the backed up data
        without the encryption keys. Of course, you won't be able to recover
        your files without the keys either, so you must make a conventional,
        secure, backup of these keys.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Authentication</title>

        <para>SSL certificates are used to authenticate clients. UNIX user
        accounts are not used to minimise the dependence on the configuration
        of the operating system hosting the server.</para>

        <para>A script is provided to run the necessary certification
        authority with minimal effort.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Server daemon</title>

      <para>The server daemon is designed to be simple to deploy, and run on
      the cheapest hardware possible. To avoid the necessity to use expensive
      hardware RAID or software RAID with complex setup, it (optionally)
      stores files using RAID techniques.</para>

      <para>It does not need to run as a privileged user.</para>

      <para>Each account has a set amount of disc space allocated, with a soft
      and a hard limit. If the account exceeds the soft limit, a housekeeping
      process will start deleting old versions and deleted files to reduce the
      space used to below the soft limit. If the backup client attempts to
      upload a file which causes the store to exceed the hard limit, the
      upload will be refused.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Building and installing</title>

    <section>
      <title>Before you start</title>

      <para>Firstly, check that all the clocks on your clients, servers and
      signing machines are accurate and in sync. A disagreement in time
      between a client and a server is the biggest cause of installation
      difficulties, as the times in the generated certificates will cause
      login failures if the start date is in the future.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Box Backup compile</title>

      <para>In the following instructions, replace 0.00 with the actual
      version number of the archive you have downloaded.</para>

      <para>For help building on Windows, see the <link linkend="AppB">Windows
      Compile Appendix</link>. And if you want to build a Linux RPM, <link
      linkend="AppC">look here</link>.</para>

      <para>You need the latest version of OpenSSL, as some of the extra APIs
      it provides are required. You should have this anyway, as earlier
      versions have security flaws. (If you have an earlier version installed,
      the configuration script will give you instructions on enabling
      experimental support for older versions.)</para>

      <para>See <link linkend="AppA">OpenSSL notes</link> for more information
      on OpenSSL issues.</para>

      <para>There are some notes in the archive about compiling on various
      platforms within the boxbackup-0.00 directory -- read them first. For
      example, if you are compiling under Linux, look for LINUX.txt as
      boxbackup-0.00/LINUX.txt after untaring the archive.</para>

      <para>Download the archive, then in that directory type</para>

      <programlisting>tar xvzf boxbackup-0.00.tgz
cd boxbackup-0.00
./configure
make</programlisting>

      <para>The server and client will be built and packaged up for
      installation on this machine, or ready to be transferred as tar files to
      another machine for installation.</para>

      <para>This builds two parcels of binaries and scripts, 'backup-client'
      and 'backup-server'. The generated installation scripts assumes you want
      everything installed in <emphasis
      role="bold">/usr/local/bin</emphasis></para>

      <para>Optionally, type <emphasis role="bold">make test</emphasis> to run
      all the tests.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Local installation</title>

      <para>Type <emphasis role="bold">make install-backup-client</emphasis>
      to install the backup client.</para>

      <para>Type <emphasis role="bold">make install-backup-server</emphasis>
      to install the backup server.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Remote installation</title>

      <para>In the parcels directory, there are tar files for each parcel. The
      name reflects the version and platform you have built it for.</para>

      <para>Transfer this tar file to the remote server, and unpack it, then
      run the install script. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>tar xvzf boxbackup-0.00-backup-server-OpenBSD.tgz
cd boxbackup-0.00-backup-server-OpenBSD
./install-backup-server</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configure options</title>

      <para>You can use arguments to the configure script to adjust the
      compile and link lines in the generated Makefiles, should this be
      necessary for your platform. The configure script takes the usual GNU
      autoconf arguments, a full list of which can be obtained with <emphasis
      role="bold">--help</emphasis>. Additional options for Box Backup
      include:</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry char="-">--enable-gnu-readline</entry>

              <entry>Use GNU readline if present. Linking Box Backup against
              GNU readline may create licence implications if you then
              distribute the binaries. libeditline is also supported as a safe
              alternative, and is used by default if available.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>--disable-largefile</entry>

              <entry>Omit support for large files</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>--with-bdb-dir=DIR</entry>

              <entry>Specify Berkeley DB location</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>--with-random=FILE</entry>

              <entry>Use FILE as random number seed (normally
              auto-detected)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>--with-tmp-dir=DIR</entry>

              <entry>Directory for temporary files (normally /tmp)</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>See <link linkend="AppA">OpenSSL notes</link> for the OpenSSL
      specific options.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tests</title>

      <para>There are a number of unit tests provided. To compile and run one
      type:</para>

      <programlisting>./runtest.pl bbackupd release
./runtest.pl common debug
./runtest.pl ALL</programlisting>

      <para>The runtest.pl script will compile and run the test. The first
      argument is the test name, and the second the type of build. Use ALL as
      a test name to run all the tests.</para>

      <para>The output from the tests is slightly muddled using this script.
      If you're developing, porting or trying out new things, it might be
      better to use the following scheme:</para>

      <programlisting>cd test/bbackupd
make
cd ../../debug/test/bbackupd
./t</programlisting>

      <para>or in release mode...</para>

      <programlisting>cd test/bbackupd
make -D RELEASE
cd ../../release/test/bbackupd
./t</programlisting>

      <para>(use RELEASE=1 with GNU make)</para>

      <para>I tend to use two windows, one for compilation, and one for
      running tests.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <appendix>
    <title id="AppA">Box Backup and SSL</title>

    <section>
      <title>General notes</title>

      <para>Ideally, you need to use version 0.9.7 or later of OpenSSL. If
      this is installed on your system by default (and it is on most recent
      releases of UNIX like OSes) then everything should just work.</para>

      <para>However, if it isn't, you have a few options.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Upgrade your installation</title>

        <para>The best option is to upgrade your installation to use 0.9.7.
        Hopefully your package manager will make this easy for you. This may
        require reinstallation of lots of software which depends on OpenSSL,
        so may not be ideal.</para>

        <para>(But as there have been a few security flaws in OpenSSL
        recently, you probably want to upgrade it anyway.)</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Install another OpenSSL</title>

        <para>The second best option is to install another copy. If you
        download and install from source, it will probably install into
        /usr/local/ssl. You can then configure Box Backup to use it
        using:</para>

        <programlisting>./configure --with-ssl-headers=/usr/local/ssl/include --with-ssl-lib=/usr/local/ssl/lib</programlisting>

        <para>which will set up the various includes and libraries for
        you.</para>

        <para>The configuration scripts may be a problem, depending on your
        installation. See below for more information.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Use the old version of OpenSSL</title>

        <para>If you have an old version installed, the configuration script
        will give you instructions on how to enable support for older
        versions. Read the warnings, and please, whatever you do, don't
        release binary packages or ports which enable this option.</para>

        <para>You may have issues with the configuration scripts, see
        below.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>If you have problems with the config scripts</title>

      <para>If you get OpenSSL related errors with the configuration scripts,
      there are two things to check:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The bin directory within your OpenSSL directory is in the path
          (if you have installed another version)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You have an openssl.cnf file which works and can be
          found.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title>OpenSSL config file</title>

        <para>You need to have an openssl.cnf file. The default will generally
        work well (see example at end). Make sure the openssl utility can find
        it, either set the OPENSSL_CONF environment variable, or install it
        into the location that is mentioned in the error messages.</para>

        <para>Example OpenSSL config file:</para>

        <programlisting id="openssl.cnf" xreflabel="openssl.cnf">#
# OpenSSL example configuration file.
# This is mostly being used for generation of certificate requests.
# 

RANDFILE                = /dev/arandom

####################################################################
[ req ]
default_bits            = 1024
default_keyfile         = privkey.pem
distinguished_name      = req_distinguished_name
attributes              = req_attributes

[ req_distinguished_name ]
countryName                     = Country Name (2 letter code)
#countryName_default            = AU
countryName_min                 = 2
countryName_max                 = 2

stateOrProvinceName             = State or Province Name (full name)
#stateOrProvinceName_default    = Some-State

localityName                    = Locality Name (eg, city)

0.organizationName              = Organization Name (eg, company)
#0.organizationName_default     = Internet Widgits Pty Ltd

# we can do this but it is not needed normally :-)
#1.organizationName             = Second Organization Name (eg, company)
#1.organizationName_default     = CryptSoft Pty Ltd

organizationalUnitName          = Organizational Unit Name (eg, section)
#organizationalUnitName_default =

commonName                      = Common Name (eg, fully qualified host name)
commonName_max                  = 64

emailAddress                    = Email Address
emailAddress_max                = 64

[ req_attributes ]
challengePassword               = A challenge password
challengePassword_min           = 4
challengePassword_max           = 20

unstructuredName                = An optional company name

[ x509v3_extensions ]

nsCaRevocationUrl               = http://www.cryptsoft.com/ca-crl.pem
nsComment                       = "This is a comment"

# under ASN.1, the 0 bit would be encoded as 80
nsCertType                      = 0x40</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </appendix>

  <appendix>
    <title id="AppB">Compiling bbackupd on Windows using Visual C++</title>

    <para>This Appendix explains how to build the bbackupd daemon for Windows
    using the Visual C++ compiler.</para>

    <para>If you have any problems following these instructions, please sign
    up to the <ulink
    url="http://lists.warhead.org.uk/mailman/listinfo/boxbackup">mailing
    lis</ulink>t and report them to us, or send an email to <ulink
    url="mailto:bbwiki@qwirx.com">Chris Wilson</ulink>. Thanks!</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: bbstored will not be built
    with this process. bbstored is not currently supported on Windows. There
    are no plans for bbstored support on Windows.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Tools</title>

      <para>You will need quite a bit of software to make this work. All of it
      is available for free on the Internet, although Visual C++ Express has
      license restrictions and a time limit.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Visual C++</title>

        <para>Microsoft's Visual C++ compiler and development environment are
        part of their commercial product <ulink
        url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/">Visual Studio</ulink>. Visual
        Studio 2005 is supported, and 2003 should work as well.</para>

        <para>You can also <ulink
        url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/express/visualc/download/">download</ulink>
        a free copy of Visual C++ 2005 Express. This copy must be registered
        (activated) within 30 days, and is free for one year.</para>

        <para>You will need the <ulink
        url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/express/visualc/usingpsdk/">Platform
        SDK</ulink> to allow you to compile Windows applications.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Perl</title>

        <para>Download and install <ulink
        url="http://www.activestate.com/Products/ActivePerl/">ActivePerl for
        Windows</ulink>, which you can probably find <ulink
        url="http://downloads.activestate.com/ActivePerl/Windows/5.6/ActivePerl-5.6.1.638-MSWin32-x86.msi">here</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Libraries</title>

        <para>You will need to download and install several libraries. They
        must all be built in the same directory, to be able to link
        properly.</para>

        <para>Choose a directory where you will unpack and compile OpenSSL,
        Zlib and Box Backup. We will call this the base directory. An example
        might be:</para>

        <programlisting>C:\Documents and Settings\Your Username\Desktop\Box</programlisting>

        <para>Make sure you know the full path to this directory.</para>

        <section>
          <title>OpenSSL</title>

          <para>You will need to compile OpenSSL using Visual C++. The latest
          release at this time, OpenSSL 0.9.8a, does not compile with Visual
          C++ 2005 out of the box, so you need <ulink
          url="http://bbdev.fluffy.co.uk/svn/box/chris/win32/support/openssl-0.9.8a-vc2005.zip">a
          patched version</ulink>. The <ulink
          url="http://www.openssl.org/source/openssl-0.9.8a.tar.gz">original
          source</ulink> and <ulink
          url="http://bbdev.fluffy.co.uk/svn/box/chris/win32/support/openssl-0.9.8a-win32fix.patch">patch</ulink>
          are also available.</para>

          <para>To compile OpenSSL:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Use a Windows unzipper such as <ulink
              url="http://www.winzip.com/">WinZip (free trial)</ulink> to
              extract the <emphasis
              role="bold">openssl-0.9.8a-vc2005.tar.gz</emphasis> archive,
              which you just downloaded, into the base directory.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Rename the folder from <emphasis
              role="bold">openssl-0.9.8a-vc2005</emphasis> to <emphasis
              role="bold">openssl</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Open a command shell (run <emphasis
              role="bold">cmd.exe</emphasis>) and <emphasis
              role="bold">cd</emphasis> to the openssl directory</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Run the following commands:</para>

              <programlisting>perl Configure VC-WIN32
ms\do_ms
"c:\program files\Microsoft Visual Studio 8\Common7\Tools\vsvars32.bat"
nmake -f ms\ntdll.mak</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Zlib</title>

          <para>You will need to download the <ulink
          url="http://www.zlib.net/zlib123-dll.zip">Zlib compiled DLL</ulink>.
          Create a directory called <emphasis role="bold">zlib</emphasis> in
          the base directory, and unzip the file you just downloaded into that
          directory. You don't need to compile anything.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Download Box Backup</title>

        <para>The first version of Box Backup that's known to compile and with
        Visual C++ 2005 is available on the <ulink
        url="http://bbdev.fluffy.co.uk/svn/box/chris/win32/vc2005-compile-fixes/">Subversion
        server</ulink>. However, this version has not been extensively tested
        and may be out of date.</para>

        <para>The changes are expected to be merged into the <ulink
        url="http://bbdev.fluffy.co.uk/svn/box/trunk">Subversion trunk</ulink>
        at some point, and this page should then be updated. If in doubt,
        please sign up to the <ulink
        url="http://lists.warhead.org.uk/mailman/listinfo/boxbackup">mailing
        list</ulink> and ask us.</para>

        <para>To get the source code out of Subversion you will need a <ulink
        url="http://subversion.tigris.org/files/documents/15/25364/svn-1.2.3-setup.exe">Subversion
        client for Windows</ulink>. After installing it, open a new command
        prompt, go to the base directory, and type:</para>

        <programlisting>svn co http://bbdev.fluffy.co.uk/svn/box/chris/win32/vc2005-compile-fixes/ boxbackup</programlisting>

        <para>This should create a directory called <emphasis
        role="bold">boxbackup</emphasis> inside the base directory.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Configure Box Backup</title>

        <para>Open a command prompt, change to the base directory then
        <emphasis role="bold">boxbackup</emphasis>, and run <emphasis
        role="bold">win32.bat</emphasis> to configure the sources. Otherwise,
        Visual C++ will complain about missing files whose names start with
        <emphasis role="bold">autogen</emphasis>, and missing <emphasis
        role="bold">config.h</emphasis>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Compile Box Backup</title>

        <para>Open Visual C++. Choose "File/Open/Project", navigate to the
        base directory, then to <emphasis
        role="bold">boxbackup\infrastructure\msvc\2005</emphasis> (or
        <emphasis role="bold">2003</emphasis> if using Visual Studio 2003),
        and open any project or solution file in that directory.</para>

        <para>Press F7 to compile Box Backup. If the compilation is
        successful, <emphasis
        role="bold">boxbackup\Debug\bbackupd.exe</emphasis> will be
        created.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Install Box Backup</title>

        <para>Create the destination directory, <emphasis
        role="bold">C:\Program Files\Box Backup\bbackupd</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>Write a configuration file, keys and certificate on a Unix
        machine, and copy them into the <emphasis role="bold">Box
        Backup</emphasis> directory, together with the following files from
        the base directory:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>boxbackup\Debug\bbackupd.exe</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>openssl\out32dll\libeay32.dll</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>openssl\out32dll\ssleay32.dll</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>zlib\zlib1.dll</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Ensure that the user running Box Backup can read from the
        <emphasis role="bold">Box Backup</emphasis> directory, and write to
        the <emphasis role="bold">bbackupd</emphasis> directory inside
        it.</para>

        <para>Run Box Backup by double-clicking on it, and check that it
        connects to the server. If the window opens and closes immediately,
        it's probably due to a problem with the configuration file - check the
        Windows Event Viewer for details.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Windows Service</title>

        <para>Box Backup can also run as a Windows service, in which case it
        will be automatically started at boot time in the background. To
        install this, open a command prompt, and run:</para>

        <programlisting>cd "C:\Program Files\Box Backup"
bbackupd.exe -i</programlisting>

        <para>This should output Box Backup service installed.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </appendix>

  <appendix>
    <title id="AppC">Compilation and installation by building an RPM on
    Linux</title>

    <para>It is very easy to build an RPM of Box Backup on Linux platforms.
    This should work on all Red Hat distributions (including Fedora), SuSE,
    and probably others too.</para>

    <para>Given that you have the correct development packages installed
    simply execute this command (replacing the version number):</para>

    <programlisting>rpmbuild -ta boxbackup-0.00.tgz</programlisting>

    <para>rpmbuild will report where the packages have been written to, and
    these can be installed in the normal manner.</para>

    <para>If you have never built an RPM before you should set up a convenient
    build area as described in the <ulink
    url="http://www.rpm.org/max-rpm/s1-rpm-anywhere-different-build-area.html">RPM
    book</ulink>.</para>

    <para>If you wish to customise the package you can find the spec file in
    the contrib/rpm directory.</para>
  </appendix>
</book>
