<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>bbstoreaccounts</refentrytitle>

    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>bbstoreaccounts</refname>

    <refpurpose>View and change account information on the store
    server</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>bbstoreaccounts [-c configfile] command account_id
      [command-specific arguments]</command>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsection>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para><literal>bbstoreaccounts</literal> is the tool for managing accounts
    on the store server. It can be used to view information related to
    accounts, as well as create, change and delete accounts on the store
    server. </para>

    <para><literal>bbstoreaccounts</literal> alwas takes at least 2
    parameters: the command name and the account ID. Some commands require
    additional parameters, and some commands have optional parameters.</para>

    <refsection>
      <title>Options</title>

      <para><literal>-c &lt;configfile&gt;</literal></para>

      <para>The configfile to use for connecting to the store. Default is
      <literal>/etc/box/bbstored.conf</literal>.</para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection>
      <title>Commands</title>

      <para>The commands tells bbstoreaccounts what action to perform.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><literal>check &lt;account-id&gt; [fix]</literal></para>

          <para>The <literal>check</literal> command verifies the integrity of
          the store account given, and optionally fixes any corruptions.
          <emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: It is recommended to run the
          'simple' check command (without <literal>fix</literal>) before using
          the <literal>fix</literal> option, This gives an overview of the
          extent of any problems, before attempting to fix them.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>create &lt;account-id&gt; &lt;discset&gt;
          &lt;softlimit&gt; &lt;hardlimit&gt;</literal></para>

          <para>Creates a new store account with the parameters given. The
          parameters are as follows:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><literal>account-id</literal>: the ID of the new account
              to be created. A 32-bit hexadecimal number. Cannot already exist
              on the server.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><literal>discset</literal>: the disc set from
              raidfile.conf(5) where the backups for this client will be
              stored.. A number. Each RAID-file set has a number in
              raidfile.conf. This number is what's used.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><literal>softlimit</literal>: The soft limit is the amount
              of storage that the server will guarantee to be available for
              storage.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><literal>hardlimit</literal>: The amount of storage that
              the the server will allow, before rejecting uploads, and
              starting to eliminate old and deleted files to get back down to
              <literal>softlimit</literal>. </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>delete &lt;account-id&gt; [yes]</literal></para>

          <para>Deletes the account from the store server completely. Removes
          all backups and deletes all references to the account in the config
          files.</para>

          <para><literal>delete</literal> will ask for confirmation from the
          user, when called. Using the <literal>yes</literal> flag, eliminates
          that need. This is useful when deleting accounts from within a
          script or some other automated means.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>info &lt;account-id&gt;</literal></para>

          <para>Display information about the given account. Example:</para>

          <programlisting>[root]# bbstoreaccounts info 1
                  Account ID: 00000001
              Last object ID: 58757
                 Blocks used: 9864063 (38531.50Mb)
    Blocks used by old files: 62058 (242.41Mb)
Blocks used by deleted files: 34025 (132.91Mb)
  Blocks used by directories: 6679 (26.09Mb)
            Block soft limit: 11796480 (46080.00Mb)
            Block hard limit: 13107200 (51200.00Mb)
         Client store marker: 1139559852000000 </programlisting>

          <para>Explanation:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Account ID: The account ID being displayed.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Last Object ID: A counter that keeps track of the objects
              that have been backed up. This number refers to the last file
              that was written to the store. The ID is displayed as a decimal
              number, and the object ID can be converted to a path name to a
              file as follows: convert the number to hex (e.g.: 58757 =&gt;
              0xE585); The last backed up file will be (relative from the
              client's store root): <literal>e5/o85.rfw</literal>. Longer
              numbers infer more directories in the structure, so as an
              example 3952697264 as the last object ID gives 0xEB995FB0, which
              translates to a backup pathname of
              <literal>eb/99/5f/ob0.rfw.</literal></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Blocks used: The number of blocks used by the store. The
              size in Mb depends on the number of blocks, as well as the block
              size for the disc set given in
              <literal>raidfile.conf(5)</literal>. In this case the block size
              is 4096.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Blocks used by old files: The number of blocks occupied by
              files that have newer versions in the store. This data is at
              risk for being removed during housekeeping.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Blocks used by deleted files: The number of blocks used by
              files that have been deleted on the client. Thi s data is at
              risk for being removed during housekeeping.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Blocks used by directories: The number of blocks used by
              directories in the store.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Block soft limit: The soft limit in blocks. The soft limit
              is the maximum guaranteed storage space available to the
              account. When housekeeping starts, and the old and deleted files
              are removed, they are removed in chronological order (oldest
              first), until the data used is less than the soft limit.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Block hard limit: The hard limit in blocks. The hard limit
              is the most amount of storage the server will allow in an
              account. Any data above this amount will be rejected.
              Housekeeping will reduce the storage use, so more data can be
              uploaded.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Client store marker: TODO What exactly is this? </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>setlimit &lt;account-id&gt; &lt;softlimit&gt;
          &lt;hardlimit&gt;</literal></para>

          <para>Changes the storage space allocation for the given account. No
          server restart is needed.</para>

          <para>Parameters:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><literal>account-id</literal>: the ID of the new account
              to be created. A 32-bit hexadecimal number. Cannot already exist
              on the server.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><literal>softlimit</literal>: The soft limit is the amount
              of storage that the server will guarantee to be available for
              storage.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><literal>hardlimit</literal>: The amount of storage that
              the the server will allow, before rejecting uploads, and
              starting to eliminate old and deleted files to get back down to
              <literal>softlimit</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </refsection>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Author</title>

    <para>Ben Summers and contributors. For help, please go to the <ulink
    url="http://www.boxbackup.org/trac/">Wiki</ulink>, or subscribe to the Box
    Backup <ulink
    url="http://lists.warhead.org.uk/mailman/listinfo/boxbackup">mailing
    list.</ulink></para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>See Also</title>

    <para><literal>bbstored.conf(5)</literal></para>

    <para><literal>raidfile.conf(5)</literal></para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Files</title>

    <para><literal>bbstoreaccounts</literal> uses the Box Backup server
    configuration file, usually located in
    <filename>/etc/box/bbstored.conf</filename>. </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Bugs</title>

    <para>If you find a bug in Box Backup, and you want to let us know about
    it, join the <ulink
    url="http://lists.warhead.org.uk/mailman/listinfo/boxbackup">mailing
    list</ulink>, and send a description of the problem there.</para>

    <para>To report a bug, give us at least the following information:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The version of Box Backup you are running</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The platform you are running on (Hardware and OS), for both
        client and server.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If possible attach your config files (bbstored.conf,
        bbackupd.conf) to the bug report.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Also attach any log file output that helps shed light on the
        problem you are seeing.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>And last but certainly not least, a description of what you are
        seeing, in as much detail as possible.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
</refentry>
